A Guide to the Elden E. Billings Collection, 1862-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- Series V: Publications
  - Civil War Times Illustrated (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Color Bearer (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Columbia Historical Society (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Confederate Historical Institute "Dispatch" (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Foraging the Books (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Fort Ward Dispatch (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Franklin Co. Historical Society (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Franklin Flyer, 1968-1976 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Franklin Flyer (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Friends of Virginia Civil War Parks (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Fury (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - The Grand Review, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Grant Cottage Chronicles (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Harper's New Monthly, 1850-1855 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Harper's New Monthly, 1856-1861 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Harper's New Monthly, 1862-1865 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Harper's New Monthly, 1866-1869 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Harper's New Monthly, 1870-1875 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Harper's New Monthly, 1876-1879 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Harper's New Monthly, 1880-1885 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Harper's Weekly, 1861 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Heliogram (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Historic Lexington Foundation (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Loyal Legion Historical Journal (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Journal of the Military Service Institute, 1887-1894 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Journal of the Military Service Institute, 1895-1899 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Journal of the Military Service Institute, 1900-1902 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Journal of the U. S. Infantry Association, 1909 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - U. S. Army Military History Institute (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - U. S. Service Magazine, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - The Maryland Line (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Museum Graphic, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Newsletters, Various (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Pathways (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Pictorial Review, June 1917. (Box 17)
  - Rebel Yell (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Society for Correct Civil War Information (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Society News and Views (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Surrant Courier and Society News (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Valley Echo News (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Virginia Canals and Navigation Society (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Whitehead & Hoag Co., Catalog page (Box 17)
- Series VI: Primary Documents
  - Subseries A: Scrapbooks, 1858-1931, n.d.
    - Army War College, Study on Civil War, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Joe Hooker Post Minutes, N.J., 1887-1889 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Large scrapbook, 118th Regiment, Ohio Volunteer Infantry, 60 typewritten letters by or to - 2 Large Scrapbooks (Box 20)
    - Benton L. Thompson, 1862-1865 (Box 14)
    - Scrapbook – unknown owner, 1889-1910 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook, newsclippings - unknown owner, 1890 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, news clippings, 1858-1904 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - History of the 73rd Indiana Regiment by E. K. Barnhill (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Washington Light Infantry Scrapbook (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Manuscripts, 1861-1924, n.d.
    - Allan, Joe M., Abbyville, Miss., Dec. 15, 1862 to his cousin Charlene Morgan, in Minn. Allan describes war, traitors, rebels deserting, burning bridges, describes his tent and "two black boys who do our cooking and take care of our horses." Also mentions Grand Junction and Maj. Gen. U. S. Grant (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Bevel, G. A. (?) to 'Tom,' writes of service in the Confederacy until Jan. '63 when he 'played quits, scouting four months in Tenn. And then went 'over Cumberland Mountain into the Federal line,", 1866 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Bierce, L. V., 3 letters, 2 written in 1870, 1 possibly earlier and possibly to Lincoln? (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Binion, James, 10th Ga Infantry, in Virginia, typed copies, 1861-1864 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Bryant, Corp., S.O., 20th Michigan Infantry, typed,, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Burns, Calvin J., copies of letters, 1864 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Burr, 'no first name,' Washington, D.C., Lincoln's death, April 28, 1865 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Butler, Calvin to his brother W. A. Wolcott, Mass. Original, 1864 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Carpenter, Lyman, writes from TN to his sister about battles in TN and getting smallpox and typhoid, typed, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Chancellorsville Letter, typed, from Camp Convalescent, June 2, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Civil War Diary of G. W. Pennington,, 1862-1865 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Clift, R. H. to his mother, typed, re: Battle of Murfreesboro, January 10, 1862 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Cluseret, Gutave-Paul, handwritten transcription of letters by Billings (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Crawford, Samuel Wylie to George W. Reed original letter written from Huntsville Ala. Wylie reminisces about Sheridan's last campaign, July 10, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Curtis, Lyman to Susan, original letter, writes about loss of son in battle,, August 28, 1864 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Curtis, Gen. Samuel Ryan, typed copy of letter to his nephew,, July 30, 1862 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Denver, Gen., letter on Sherman's March into Miss., original, 1875 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Diaries, Memories (Civil War era) – all reproduced, transcribed, typed (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Eliza – ltr from, to sister and aunt, writes about Christmas, original, December 26, 1867 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Gillette, James (Capt. C.S.) writes to his mother about Battle of Chancelorsville,, May 9, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Grant, U.S. to Major Gen. W. Sherman, copy of original, December 18, 1864 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Hyde, John E. (Private) of Mississippi, typed copies, 1865 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Ladies Association for Soldiers' Relief,, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Letters, assorted Civil War, all copies (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Letter, Civil War, copy of – brother Phil to brother unknown, 1862 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Letter, partial to 'Bro' from 'unknown,' Lancaster, mentions 'Alexandria,', September 10, 1862 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Letter from son to father, Gainesville, Ga. Letterhead designates 'Office of Commissioner of Railroads' and son writes of horse and cost of hay, peas, sugar, September 19, 1899 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Letters, 4 original to Josie from Miranda – religious in subjects,, 1865 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Letter to Abraham Lincoln, unsigned, n.d., subject hospitals and religion (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Manassas Junction, original letter from John 'undeciphered,' writes he had measles, the battle at Manassas, wounded, a 'Ball' in Fairfax and the ladies, July 28, 1861 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Mansfield, Richard H. cartoonist, his cartoons from newspaper (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - McCarthy, John B. (?) Rockford, Illinois original letter, Aug. 31 '?', to '?' Clark writes about Mr. and Mrs. Lincoln (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Merrick, C. Henry, 6 original letters, 1862, 1863, 1864, 1865, 1869 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Nine Mile Road, letter, brother to sister, July 1862 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Pace, Thomas N., Indiana Volunteers, Certificate of Service (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Phelps, Walter (copies of letters), 1861-1862 (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - Quartermaster Receipt, blank, Confederate States (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Reckmeyer, W., typed/translated, TN, 1861 (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - Sackey, John to his cousin Miss Mattie Turner, original letter from Camp Near Winchester Virginia, writes that he is weak from being sick, August 3, 1861 (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - Sewells Point Battery letter from L. C. Jones, discusses artillery, July 1, 1861 (Box 12, Folder 38)
    - Sherman, W. T. Gen., (copies of letters), 1863, 1864, 1888 (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - Sherman, W. T., signed by Sherman but written by unknown, 1887 (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - Struthers, Jeannie Gourlay to Allen Clark, [Lincoln flag], 1924 (Box 12, Folder 41)
    - Taliaferro, W. B. to General W. W. Loring, typed, January 29, 1862 (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - Warner, Charles, 145th N.Y. Reg., letters typed and transcribed, 1862-1863 (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - Wiggenton, Thomas S.R. to Capt. J. Thomas Clark, original letter written at Racoonford, VA writes about death, wounds and captures, August 20, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Wolcott, I. H. P., original letters, plus typed and transcribed copies, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 45)
- Series VII: Artifacts
  - 1 Jackson (Box 20)
  - 1 Lee (Box 20)
  - Collectibles, various (Box 19)
  - Daguerrotypes (4), Calling Cards, Medallions (Box 22)
  - Elephant Fight, print from Chandni Chowk, Delhi (Box 17)
  - Notebook of U.S. Grant III (Box 21)
  - Stamps of the Civil War (Box 17)